בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today is דף daf, *Daf* ס"ג *Samech Gimmel*
63. We've begun מרובה *Meruba*, so I wasn't here yesterday, so just
to say if it wasn't said, you know we now move from
the first half of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* to the second half
of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* although in the seventh פרק *Perek*, so
פרקים *Perakim*-wise it's a little more than half. The first half is
about נזקי ממון *Nizkei Mamon* when your property does damage, it also
is when you do damage to property but it's about damages. The
second half is about burglary and theft, גניבה gneivah, *Gneiva* and גזילה
*Gzeila*, and also about personal injury when a person injures another person's
body stuff that we've dealt with before but not in a focused
way and that's really the whole second half of בבא קמא *Bava
Kamma* so very different set of topics. And מרובה *Meruba*, which you'll
see is a lot about גניבה *Gneiva* and paying כפל kefel *Kefel*
as the משנה *Mishna* opens, you know that you pay double for
you know you paid more cases you pay double for when you
do גניבה *Gneiva*. גניבה *Gneiva* is burglary and I'm going to use
some terms in a very specific way. Okay, burglary is when is
גניבה *Gneiva* is when basically sneak into somebody's house and steal their
things you do not outright grab it from them. גזילה *Gzeila* is
theft. Okay, so theft as opposed to burglary. Burglary you pay double
and if it's a an ox or a sheep and you slaughter
or you sell it you would pay four or five times as
much. Okay, and that's going to be the focus of מרובה *Meruba*.
גזילה *Gzeila* will come up in a later פרק *Perek* although there's
obviously going to be an ongoing comparison between the two. Now the
מרובה *Meruba* also is like a classic ישיבה *Yeshiva* מסכתא *Masechta* and
we'll see why when we get a little bit more into it.
But when they learn this in the ישיבה *Yeshiva* they tend to
skip the first two דף *Daf* okay which is what we're doing
because the first two דף *Daf* are about a lot of like
דרשות *Drosos* of כלל ופרט וכלל Klal U'prat U'klal, *Klal u'prat u'klal*,
how do you know to include all types of objects are חייב
*Chayav* in גניבה *Gneiva* not just a שור Shor *Shor* not just
an ox or donkey like mentioned in the פסוקים pesukim, *Psukim* and
so on. So all this like כלל ופרט וכלל Klal U'prat U'klal,
*Klal u'prat u'klal* at the end of the day to get that
you're liable for all objects when it comes to paying double that's
today's דף *Daf* and tomorrow's דף *Daf* and is largely skipped in
the ישיבות *Yeshivot* so I'm just going to warn you it's not
going to be that intellectually stimulating I mean maybe some people get
into it but that's what we've got. But after that we're going
to get into the פרק *Perek* that is really like a very
very classic ישיביש *Yeshivish* מסכתא *Masechta*. Okay, so let's pick up at
the top of ס"ג עמוד א Samech Gimmel Amud Aleph. *Samech Gimmel
Amud Aleph*. The question at hand is how do you know that
you pay כפל kefel, *Kefel* for all objects? Now the פסוקים pesukim?
*Psukim* in the תורה *Torah* say the following.
What? גניבה *Gneiva*. When you burgled? Did I say steal? I should
say burgle. Trying to be precise here. So the פסוקים psukim. *Psukim*
in the תורה *Torah* say following: כי יתן איש אל רעהו ki
yiten ish el re'ehu, כסף או כלים kesef o kelim. לשמור lishmor,
וגנב מבית האיש אם ימצא הגנב ישלם שנים im yimatze haganav yeshallem
shenayim. *Ki yiten
ish el re'ehu kesef o
kelim lishmor ve'gunav mibeit ha'ish im yimatze haganav yeshalem shnayim*.
So right there it talks about paying double if something is נגנב
nignav *Nignav* is burgled okay so the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is כי
יתן איש אל רעהו ki yiten ish el re’eihu. *Ki yiten ish
el re'ehu* כי יתן איש אל רעהו *Ki yiten ish el re'ehu*
and now here's the key stuff about what are the objects so
it says כסף או כלים kesef o-chelim, לשמור *Kesef o kelim lishmor*.
So that's very not even animals it's very general right right וגנב
מבית האיש *ve'gunav mibeit ha'ish* וגנב *ve'gunav* okay וגנב *ve'gunav* and מבית
האיש *mibeit ha'ish* and ישלם שנים yeshallem shenayim. *yeshalem shnayim*.
So okay that's one place where you pay כפל kefel *Kefel* straight
thing was stolen ישלם שנים yeshalem shnayim. *yeshalem shnayim* and it's כסף
kesef, או כלים לשמור *kesef o kelim lishmor*. Okay so that's the
first half of the פסוק Pasuk *Pasuk*. Then it says אם לא
ימצא הגנב im lo yimatze haganav, *im lo yimatze haganav* if you
don't know who the גנב gannav *Ganav* is ונקרב בעל הבית ba'al
habayis אל האלוהים *venikrav ba'al habayit el ha'elohim* you come to the
judges אם לא שלח ידו im lo shalach yado. במלאכת רעהו *im
lo shalach yado bimlechet re'ehu* and you have to take an oath
that you did not misuse your friend's property you were given this
property to watch you were not שולח יד *sholeiach yad* you did
not misuse it in any way take it for your own purpose
על כל דבר פשע al kol devar pesha, *al kol dvar pesha*
for any matter of that is potential negligence so the simple sense
here this פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is that you're taking an oath that
you were a responsible שומר shomer *Shomer* you did not use it
for yourself you were not negligent and now it says it increases
what you're taking an oath about okay so it says ונקרב בעל
הבית *venikrav ba'al habayit* okay בעל הבית *ba'al habayit* אל האלוהים *el
ha'elohim* אם לא Lo, שלח ידו *im lo shalach yado* אם לא
שלח ידו *im lo shalach yado* okay
now it says here is the list of things okay על כל
דבר פשע al kol dvar pesha? *al kol dvar pesha* על כל
דבר פשע kol devar pesha, *al kol dvar pesha* על שור al
shor *al shor* על חמור al chamor *al chamor* what is it
על שור al shor *al shor* על חמור al chamor *al chamor*
על שה al seh *al seh* על שלמה al salmah *al salma*
על כל אבידה Al Kol Aveidah, *al kol aveida*. על
כל אבידה al kol aveidah. *Al kol aveida* is a little weird
here because you were given an object to watch why is it
calling it an אבידה aveidah *aveida*? Anyway אשר יאמר כי הוא זה
asher yomar ki hu zeh. עד האלוהים יבוא דבר שניהם *asher yomar
ki hu zeh ad ha'elohim yavo dvar shneihem*. אשר ירשיעון אלוהים asher
yarshi'un elohim ישלם שניים לרעהו. yeshalem shnayim l're'ehu. Now,
the funny thing is who's paying double? What does it mean אשר
ירשיעון אלוהים ישלם שניים לרעהו? yeshalem shnayim l're'ehu? If you were a
bad שומר shomer. you have to pay double, right? Is it saying
now and what does it mean and so like what exactly is
going on there? So, what חז"ל chazal are going to say happened
here is, they're going to interpret this as a case of
טוען טענת גנב. to'en ta'anat gannav. גנב gannav? isn't found, but how
do we know there's a גנב? gannav, Because you took an oath
and you said oh yes, it was stolen, I didn't do anything
wrong. If you're lying and not that you were negligent, but you're
lying because it was never stolen because you were the one who
kept it for yourself, so the הלכה halakha is if you take
an oath that it was stolen and when or that it was
burgled and you're the burglar, you're the one who took it, you're
treated in הלכה halakha like you committed the burglary. So you will
be paid double if you took a false oath that it was
stolen. Okay, so that's what they say that this is talking about,
they say this is talking about...
Okay, this is טוען טענת גנב ונמצא שהוא גנבו. to'en ta'anat gannav
v'nimtza shehu g'navo. Okay, that's how חז"ל chazal explain what that
second half of the פסוק pasuk. is about. Okay, so here we
got here by the actual גנב, gannav what type of objects do
you pay כפל kefel for? כסף או כלים. Here by the guy
who claims that it was stolen and he's also going to pay
כפל, kefel it's got this much longer list, על שור על חמור
על שה על שלמה al shor al chamor al seh al salmah,
על כל אבדה al kol aveidah אשר יאמר כי הוא זה. And
what our goal is going to be is to say how do
you know you pay כפל kefel. for pretty much everything, it's not
limited to this list, but these specific concrete things are going to
say that there's a handful of things you don't pay כפל kefel
for. Okay, you don't pay double for. You got the basic structure?
Okay, so let's now look at I mean... All
right, I'm just going to do it because I know that Dan
covered it but I just have to can't start in the middle.
So we're going to go back to ס"ב עמוד ב'. Samekh Bet
Amud Bet. I apologize, we'll do it quickly and we'll do ten
lines from the bottom. The two dots. מנא הני מילי. minani mili.
Okay, how do we know that you basically pay כפל kefel for
everything? Okay, מנא הני מילי. minani mili. דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabbanan, על
כל דבר פשע, kol dvar pesha, כלל, klal, a general word. על
שור shor על חמור Chamor, על שה al seh על שלמה, al
salmah, פרט. prat. על כל אבדה, al kol aveidah, חזר וכלל. chazar
v'klal. Right, so it's in this, this is the כלל, klal, כל
Kol
דבר
פשע, this is the פרט, prat, על שור על חמור chamor? על
שה Seh על שלמה, Salmah and this is על כל אבדה, al
kol aveidah, חזר וכלל. chazar v'klal. כלל פרט וכלל. klal prat u'klal.
Okay, חזר וכלל, chazar v'klal,
כלל פרט וכלל, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט, klal prat u-chlal
ee ata dan ela k'ein ha-prat. so it's only things that are
like the concrete objects. מה הפרט מפורש דבר המטלטל וגופו ממון, ma
haprat meforash davar hametaltel v'gufo mamon, the same way these things in
the list are chattels, they're not land, and they have intrinsic value,
אף כל דבר המטלטל וגופו ממון. af kol davar hametaltel v'gufo mamon.
That includes anything of that like that is chattels and has intrinsic
value, if you steal it you pay כפל. kefel יצאו קרקעות שאינן
מטלטלין, yatz'u karka'ot she'einan metaltelin, so you would not pay כפל kefel
if you were a גנב gannav on land which is not chattels.
Now, how are you a גנב gannav? on land? Right, I could
be a גזלן gazlan on land I suppose, I could seize property
and claim that it's mine,
you know, whatever, but I don't know, kick you out of your
house. How are you a גנב? gannav; We understand the difference a
גנב; gannav a גנב gannav means like surreptitiously, right? So how and
you're not directly stealing it from somebody. So if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, יצאו קרקעות, yatz'u karka'ot, look at this little תוספות. Tosafot.
ואם תאמר, v'im tomar, I'm sorry, where is... oh, not that תוספות,
Tosafot, he says...
oh, yes, four lines from the bottom of the דף, in the
middle of the תוספות, Tosafot, ואם תאמר, v'im tomar, middle of the
line, וגניבה בקרקע היכי שייכא? v'gneiva b'karka heichi shaycha? How do you
burgle land, like that you need to say you don't pay כפל
kefel if you're a גנב gannav on land? How can you be
a גנב ganav on land? So ויש לומר במסיג גבול. v'yesh lomar
b'massig g'vul. I love that answer. It's like you switch the boundary
marker, so now you have taken somebody else's land and they're clueless
about it. It's like he snuck into their house, they have no
idea that you did it, they're not aware that you moved the
boundary marker, okay? אי נמי במחובר לקרקע. i nami b'mechubar l'karka. Or
like basically something was attached to the ground and you let's say
you stole the person's grape vines, you ripped them out of the
ground or something of that nature. Okay, so one thing we're excluding
is כפל Kefel. from land,
back to the גמרא, Gemara, יצאו קרקעות שאינן מטלטלין, yatz'u karka'ot she'einan
metaltelin, יצאו עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות, yatz'u avadim shehukshu l'karka'ot, and
we also want to exclude slaves because they're connected to land. יצאו
שטרות, yatz'u shtarot, and you will exclude IOU documents, שאף על פי
שמטלטלין אין גופן ממון, she'af al pi shemetaltelin ein gufan mamon, even
though they're chattels
they don't have intrinsic value and therefore you also do not pay
כפל kefel on those. Okay, יצא הקדש. yatz'a hekdesh. Now you also
don't pay כפל kefel on הקדש, hekdesh, רעהו כתיב. re'ehu ketiv. It
says כי יתן איש אל רעהו, okay?
So therefore you're not going to pay if you steal from הקדש
hekdesh or you burgle from הקדש hekdesh you're not going to pay
double. Okay, so that's what we exclude. exclude, but we basically include
everything else. So now the גמרא Gemara says, no, one minute. אם
אמרת פרט למפורש אבל שנבילתו מטמא, Im Amarta Prat L'meforash Aval She'neveilato
Metamei, this might sound familiar, we've gone through this in other cases.
מאי Mai maybe we'll limit it to things like the animals that
are in the this list, and these are animals שנבילתו מטמא במגע
ובמשא, She'neveilato Metamei B'maga U'v'masa, that if you touch their corpse you
you become טמא. Tamei. אף כל דבר שנבילתו מטמא במגע ובמשא, Af
Kol Davar She'neveilato Metamei B'maga U'v'masa, maybe only animals that if you
touch their corpse you become טמא? Tamei? אבל עופות לא, Aval Ofos
Lo, but birds it you don't become טמא Tamei by contact. So
therefore, how do you know to include all animals? So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute. ומי מצית אמרת הכי? U'mi Mazis Amarta Hachi?
How could you say to limit it to a subset of animals?
והא שלמה כתיב, V'ha Salmah Kesiv, one of the things in that
פסוק pasuk, is a garment. So clearly we're not limiting ourselves to
the world of animals. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. אמרי אנן
בבעלי חיים קאמרינן. Amri Anan B'vaalei Chayim Ka'amrinan. No, no, no, within
the world of animals, meaning maybe some types of animals, it's a
subset of animals that you pay for, and שלמה Salmah or any
type of, like you know, of manufactured object. But maybe you don't
read these all together, and maybe within the world of animals, you're
going to limit it to a subset. Okay, so אימא בבעלי חיים
דבר שנבילתו מטמא במגע ובמשא אין דבר שאין נבילתו מטמא במגע ובמשא
לא. Eima B'vaalei Chayim Davar She'neveilato Metamei B'maga U'v'masa In Davar She'ein
Neveilato Metamei B'maga U'v'masa Lo.
Maybe only something that, within the world of animals, only things that
corpses create טומאה Tumah through contact. Top of ס"ג עמוד א'. ודהא
כל חד וחד כלל ופרט באפי נפשיה דרשינן ליה V'ha Kol Chad
V'chad Klal U'prat Ba'apei Nafshei Darshinan Lei because everyone will sort of
say it's its own little כלל ופרט, Klal U'prat, meaning we'll look
at every, we won't, we'll sort of put all of these in
one big list, we'll look at each one of these as signifying
some universe of things. So within the universe of animals, it'll be
a subset of animals and שלמה salma, will be for non-animals.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אבל עופות לא, Aval Ofos Lo, but
birds maybe are not, you wouldn't pay כפל. kefel No. אם כן,
Im Kein, if that's true, נכתוב רחמנא חד פרטא. Nichtov Rachmana Chad
Prata. Then you wouldn't need to say, you wouldn't need to say
all these things, שור חמור ושה. Shor Chamor V'seh.
Just one of those if you wanted to limit it to a
subset of animals. So the גמרא Gemara says, היי נכתוב רחמנא? Hai
Nichtov Rachmana? Which one should it write? אי כתב רחמנא שור? Ei
Kasav Rachmana Shor? Had it just written Ox and then I should
say that'll get me a certain subset of animals? No, that would
have been even a smaller subset. הוה אמינא, Hava Amina, I would
have said קרב לגבי מזבח אין, Karev Legabei Mizbeiach In, only animals
that could be brought as sacrifices. שאין קרב לגבי מזבח לא, She'ein
Karev Legabei Mizbeiach Lo, but not animals that can't be brought as
sacrifices. So therefore it had to write another animal. So אי כתב
רחמנא חמור? Ei Kasav Rachmana Chamor? Now so, a donkey. Donkey can't
be brought as on the altar. So that comes to include even
animals, you know, that are not brought as a sacrifice. But even
it just written donkey, הוה אמינא, Hava Amina, I would have said
קדוש בבכורה אין, Kadosh B'vechorah In, only animals that are sanctified as
the firstborn because a donkey's included in that. שאין קדוש בבכורה לא,
She'ein Kadosh B'vechorah Lo, and those that are not sanctified as a
firstborn, no. Okay, so therefore it had to write שור וחמור. Shor
V'chamor. So anyway, אם
כן נכתוב רחמנא שור וחמור. Im Kein Nichtov Rachmana Shor V'chamor.
All right,
but just write שור and חמור, chamor, then it would have not
limited to altar, not limited to things sanctified on the מזבח, Mizbeiach,
and maybe שה Seh? is coming to include all animals? Not necessarily.
שה למה לי? Seh L'mai Li? Why is it coming to write
שה? seh, שמע מינה לאתויי עופות. Shma Mina L'asuyei Ofos. Maybe that's
coming to include even birds. Maybe not. ואימא לאתויי עופות טהורים. V'eima
L'asuyei Ofos Tehorim. Fine, maybe it'll include kosher birds. דומיא דשה דמטמא
בגדים בבית הבליעה Dumya D'seh D'metamei Vegadim B'veis Habliah because at least
kosher birds do cause טומאה, Tumah, not when you touch them, but
when you swallow them. They make you טמא Tamei and they make
your clothes טמא. Tamei. אבל עופות טמאים, Aval Ofos Temei'im,
but how about non-kosher birds? דלית בהו טומאה. D'leis Behu Tumah. It's
a little ironic. עופות טמאים דלית בהו טומאה. Ofos Temei'im D'leis Behu
Tumah. But טמאים Temei'im in the first half means non-kosher birds. Non-kosher
birds that do not cause טומאה. Tumah. דלא מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה
D'lo Metamei Vegadim B'veis Habliah and they do not make you and
your clothes טמא Tamei when you swallow them. לא, maybe maybe not.
So basically, why don't I read these three animals as describing the
world of animals, but still limit it to animals that cause טומאה?
Tumah? And how do I know to include all animals, even birds,
non-kosher birds that don't cause טומאה? Tumah? So it says, כל ריבויא
הוא. Kol Ribuya Hu. When it says על כל אבידה, al kol
aveidah? that's not just a כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal U'prat U'klal, כל
Kol means everything. So כל Kol is supposed to be read more
expansively. Don't read it in the narrow confines of כלל ופרט Klal
U'prat. וכלל, כל Kol means even as broad of a category as
you can draw. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. וכל היכא
דכתיב כל ריבויא הוא? V'chol Heicha De'kasiv Kol Ribuya Hu? Every time
it says the word כל Kol, it's not a כלל Klal, ופרט
וכלל, it's a more expansive category? והא גבי מעשר דכתיב כל, V'ha
Gabei Ma'aser De'kasiv Kol, when by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheini it says
כל, Kol. the word כל. kol ודרשינן ליה בכלל ופרט וכלל, U'darshinan
Lei B'klal U'prat U'klal, and we and we translate it in the
classic כלל Klal, ופרט. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa,
we've seen this before as well. ונתת הכסף, V'nasata Hakesef, you shall
give the money, oh look at that, two coffees, ברוך שכוח, Baruch
Shekoach, בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, B'chol Asher Te'aveh Nafshecha, anything your soul
desires, כלל, Klal. again a a general, and notice here בכל B'chol
is read as a כלל, klal, not as a ריבוי, Ribuy, not
as broadly inclusive, just your general כלל. klal. בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר,
B'vakar U'v'tzon U'v'yayin U'v'shachar, cattle and sheep and wine and and meat,
פרט. Prat.
פרט, prat, that's specific. ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך, u-v-chol asher tishalcha nafshecha,
again another בכל, be-chol, anything you desire, חזר וכלל, chazar ve-klal, that's
another general. So this is what you can use your מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni money for when you bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. כלל
פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. i
atta dan ela k'ein haprat, So it's a general, a specific, and
a general, it has to be similar to the specific. מה הפרט
מפורש פרי מפרי, ma ha-prat meforash pri mi-pri, the same way the
specific is a fruit of a fruit, meaning that it's something that
is not just sitting in the ground like salt, you know, ready
to be mined or something like that, or like or you know
something like a mushrooms that's a spore or something, it's a fruit
of a fruit, פרי מפרי, pri mi-pri, וגדולי
קרקע, ve-gidulei karka, and it grows from the ground, okay, so, which
would exclude fish, and you know again animals here are considered as
growing from the ground because they get their nutrients from the ground.
אף כל פרי מפרי וגדולי קרקע, af kol pri mi-pri ve-gidulei karka,
so that's what you limit what you can use your מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni for. Anyway, the point being that כל kol, here is
read as a normal כלל, klal, it's not read as a more
broadly expansive word. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama says, no,
אמי, Ami, בכל כללא הוא. be-chol klala hu. There it says with
everything, ובכל אשר תאוה נפשך. u-v-chol asher t'aveh nafshecha. That's a כלל.
klal, כל, kol, the more unmodified כל, kol everything, ריבויא הוא. ribuyah
hu. That's a ריבוי. ribuy. Okay, so again our question is how
do you know not to limit this to a subset of animals,
maybe only animals that cause טומאה? tumah? So it says the word
כל kol, is not a normal כלל, klal it's a ריבוי ribuy
and it makes it broader. And even though by מעשר שני, ma'aser
sheni, בכל be-chol is a כלל, klal, that's a בכל. be-chol. Here
it's כל, kol alright, and that's a difference. אי נמי ee nami
says the גמרא, Gemara, or if you want, where am I? ואי
בעית
אימא, ve-ee ba'it eima, if you want I'll tell you, כל כללא
הוא, kol klala hu, fine, in general כל kol, is a כלל
klal, and you don't read it more broadly expanded. מיהו, mihu, כל
דהכא ריבויא הוא, kol de-hacha ribuyah hu, here it is more broadly
expansive.
מכדי, mechdi, כתיב מיהא כלל פרט וכלל. ktiv mi-ha klal prat u-chlal.
I already got a כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-chlal up here,
דכתיב כי יתן איש אל רעהו, de-chtiv ki yiten ish el re'ehu,
כסף, כלל, כסף או כלים, פרט, prat, לשמור, חזר וכלל. chazar ve-klal.
Here you got your כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u-chlal, okay? ואי
סלקא דעתך, ve-ee salka dach-tach, האי כל דבר פשע נמי לכלל ופרט
הוא דאתא, hai kol dvar pesha nami lichlal u-prat hu de-ata, if
this is a similar type of a כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat
u-chlal, so נכתוב רחמנא להני פרטי גבי האי כלל ופרט, nichtov rachmana
le-hanei pratei gabei hai klal u-prat, write
this is all one case in the Torah. You gave the guy
the stuff to work and then he swore, why is it repeating
a list of the concrete objects down here? Just throw everything up
here in the opening framing of the פסוקים, psukim. okay? So it
must be the reason it's repeating it is, וניכתוב רחמנא להני פרטי
גבי האי כלל ופרט, u-nichtov rachmana le-hanei pratei gabei hai klal u-prat,
על כל דבר פשע למה לי, al kol dvar pesha lama li,
so why is it repeating this and using now this על כל
kol דבר פשע? שמע מינה ריבויא הוא, shma mina ribuyah hu, to
tell you up here it's a כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u-chlal,
down here it's a ריבוי. ribuy. Okay, I don't exactly get why
because we're not combining it, it tells you that, but anyway, here
we're going to read it a little more expansively. Now, by the
way, the question you could still ask is why do you need
two separate lists? And רש"י Rashi says because up here it's the
כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-chlal is to tell you about what
type of things you make a שבועה shvua on. Remember we said
ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים ve-nikrav ba'al ha-bayit el ha-elohim that you're
going to make a שבועה shvua that you didn't misuse it. So
this is telling you the things you make a שבועה shvua on
and this is telling you the things you pay כפל kefel. for,
which is a little ironic, because up here it just tells you
pay כפל keifel? and here it's the one talking about שבועה, shvua,
you would have thought to do the reverse, but okay, whatever. Anyway,
fine. השתא דאמרת, hashta de-amart, now that you've said כל ריבויא הוא,
kol ribuyah hu, so then this כל, כל דבר פשע, כל אבידה
kol aveida starts by telling you everything. So then rather than a
כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-chlal we're going to do the opposite.
You remember there's two ways of learning. כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
u-chlal is you start with the concrete and you expand it. ריבוי
ומיעוט ribuy u-mi'ut is you start with everything and then you have
to exclude. So we're saying the כל here is a ריבוי, ribuy,
starts with assuming everything. So then we're going to use this not
as the basis for abstracting, we're going to use this as the
basis for identifying specific things to exclude. We're going to come full
circle back to where we started. Okay? השתא דאמרת כל ריבויא הוא,
hashta de-amart kol ribuyah hu, כל הני פרטי למה לי, kol hanei
pratei lama li, why do I need all these specific things? So
חד למעוטי קרקע, chad le-ma'utei karka, one of them
excludes real estate, land. חד למעוטי עבדים, chad le-ma'utei avadim, one to
exclude slaves. חד למעוטי שטרות, chad le-ma'utei shtarot, one to exclude documents
which are not intrinsic value, so that's three. שור חמור ושה, shor
chamor va-seh, those exclude land, slaves, and שטרות. shtarot. What's the last
one going to
exclude? שלמה, salma למעוטי, le-ma'utei, what is the garment come to exclude
that you don't pay כפל keifel for? דבר שאינו מסוים, davar she-eino
mesuyam, something that is not well-defined. What does that mean? So you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says דבר שאינו מסוים, davar she-eino
mesuyam, רש"י Rashi says שאין לבעלים סימן בו שפטור מכפל. she-ein la-be'alim
siman bo she-patur mi-kefel. If you can't identify it as yours, you're
exempt from כפל. keifel Now the reason רש"י Rashi says that is
because in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, we also have an idea of
returning a lost object and it uses the word שלמה salma and
there the גמרא Gemara says the purpose of the word שלמה By
an אבידה aveidah. is to tell you that you only have to
return a lost object if it's identifiable. If it's not identifiable, you
don't. But תוספות Tosafot says, but what logic is that by כפל?
keifel. I mean really, like I can go ahead and go and
you know and steal something that you don't have a סימן siman
on and there's no question that you own it, but because you
don't have a סימן, siman, I'm not going to have to pay
you כפל keifel because it's like less than it's fully yours because
you can't identify it, like that doesn't make sense. So תוספות Tosafot
says, let me just read the first sentence, פירוש בקונטרס, Pirush Bakontres,
if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, דבר שאינו מסוים, davar she-eino mesuyam,
שאין הבעלים סימן בו. she-ein ha-be’alim siman bo. תקשי, tikashei, מה לי
יש בו סימן ומה לי אין בו סימן? mah li yesh bo
siman u-mah li ein bo siman? Okay, so he first goes through
a whole thing where it's not particular exactly measurable, which is also
a little bit funny. And at the end תוספות Tosafot says like
this, if you look, ועוד, v'od, like it's four lines down in
the תוספות, Tosafot, beginning of the line, דדרשינן משלמה, d'drashinan mi-salmah, he
says, ועוד היינו יכול לפרש דבר מסוים כי הך דפרק הזהב מאן
נינהו דבר מסוים לאפוקי חצי רמון וחצי אגוז ולא. v'od hayinu yachol
l'faresh davar mesuyam ki hai d'perek ha-zahav man ninu davar mesuyam l'afukei
chatzi rimon v'chatzi egoz v'lo. Like if somebody stole a half of
a pomegranate or a half of a nut. So now I don't
know what that means like a half of anything, something that normally
is whole but came in a half? Like it's very strange what
exactly we're excluding from כפל keifel. with this thing that we say
is non-specific, דבר שאינו מסוים, davar she-eino mesuyam, something that's a little
not full, not specific. Anyway, so nobody really knows exactly what that
is. Back to the גמרא. Gemara. That's what we exclude from כפל.
keifel על כל אבידה. al kol aveidah, So we've excluded here land,
slaves, documents, דבר שאינו מסוים, davar she-eino mesuyam, whatever that is. Why
do you need this other כלל, על כל אבידה? al kol aveidah
Okay. על כל אבידה, al kol aveidah what's that for? לכדרבי חייא
בר אבא, lich'derabbi Chiya bar Abba, דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן הטוען טענת גנב באבידה משלם תשלומי כפל. da'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-to’ein ta’anat ganav be-aveidah meshalem tashlumei keifel.
So this case in the Torah is כי יתן איש אל רעהו.
Somebody gave you something to watch for them, you swear falsely, you
say it was it was burgled and you're the one who took
it. Let's say we have the exact same scenario that you swore
falsely that it was נגנב nignav, and you're the one who took
it but you were not given it to watch, you found an
אבידה. aveidah So I found Chanan's wallet. Okay. And Chanan comes to
me and he says, I heard that you found my wallet. I
said yes, but such a shame a גנב ganav? came and took
it from me after I found it. And then I might have
to take even a שבועה shvua to you even though I'm a
good guy and stuff, well maybe I'm not such a good guy.
But even though presumably I'm a שומר אבידה, shomer aveidah, right, I'm
also a שומר. shomer So I have to take a שבועה shvua
to you that that's what happened. And then it turns out that
I kept it, would I pay you כפל keifel. or not? You
never gave it to me to watch, it started because I found
your object. So he says על כל אבידה aveidah. is not is
the same as שור וחמור ושה על שלמה, shor v'chamor v'seh al
salmah, are things that I found and that I'm taking an oath
about. על כל אבידה is I found an אבידה and I'm taking
an oath about whether I did my right job as being שומר
shomer it. So how do you know that הטוען טענת גנב באבידה
משלם תשלומי כפל? ha-to’ein ta’anat ganav be-aveidah meshalem tashlumei keifel? You would
pay כפל. keifel שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse says, על כל אבידה אשר
יאמר. al kol aveidah asher yomar. Okay. So that's what we basically
get. We learn from this טוען טענת גנב. to’ein ta’anat ganav. We
learn from this list that you basically take כפל keifel on pretty
much everything with a small number of very clear exceptions. That's what
we get from this, although again ironically this is about טוען טענת
גנב, to’ein ta’anat ganav, we're not focusing on this פסוק pasuk which
is straight if somebody stole it they pay כפל. keifel. Okay. But
this is anyway what we're learning as the list of things you
pay כפל keifel. for.
The reason you pay כפל keifel. on טוען טענת גנב to’ein ta’anat
ganav is because you're a גנב?
ganav Yeah, that basically since you are taking an oath that that's
what happened and you're the one that did it, if you took
an oath that it was lost or that it was נגזל, nigzal,
not נגנב, nignav, and you're the one who took it you wouldn't
pay כפל. keifel. It's sort of like, you know, you are what
you eat, you are what you נשבע. nishba. Okay. So if you
took an oath that that's what happened and you're the one who
kept it, we make it as if you did that act and
you're the גנב ganav, and you pay כפל.
kefel עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? What?
עדים זוממים?
edim zomemim? עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Oh maybe, something like that. I
never thought about it that way but in the way that an
oath is sort of a way of bearing testimony, it's an interesting
way of thinking about that. Yeah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן התם, tenan hatam,
we taught over there,
היכן פקדוני? heichan pikdoni? Somebody says, I think it's in שבועות, Shavuot,
somebody says, where is that object that I entrusted to you with
you? אמר ליה אבד, amar lei avad, it got lost. משביעך אני,
_mashbi’acha ani_, I will make you take a שבועה shvua to me.
ואמר אמן. v'amar amen. Yes. And he takes a שבועה shvua that
it was lost. ועדים מעידים אותו שאכלו הוא, v'edim me'idim oto she-achalo
hu, and witnesses testify that he kept it to himself and even,
you know, consumed it, just used it or whatever. So basically it's
just like our scenario except rather than saying it was נגנב, nignav.
you say it was lost. In that case משלם את הקרן, meshalem
et ha-keren, you don't pay כפל. kefel. Only when you take an
oath that it was נגנב. nignav Here if you take an oath
that it was lost, you don't pay כפל. kefel הודה על פי
עצמו, hodeh al pi atzmo, then you admitted that you, rather than
witnesses testify that you kept it to yourself, you came forward and
you admitted that you kept it. yourself, משלם קרן, meshallem keren, you
pay the base amount, but not only that, if you're a good
guy and you admit it, you have to pay these extra payments
because for כפרה, kapparah, it is what achieves atonement for your sin
of your false oath, not just a false oath, but a false
oath that is used to steal property from somebody else, to hold
property that's not yours. So what the Torah says you do in
that case is you pay not only the base but an extra
fifth, and אשם, asham, and you bring a sacrifice. That's a sacrifice
on אשם גזילות, asham gezelot, when you take an oath as a
way of stealing something. Okay, היכא פקדוני, heicha pikdoni, that's if you
say it was lost. Now let's say he says היכא פקדוני, heicha
pikdoni, where's my lost object? And he says לא נגנב, lo nignav,
it was burgled. משביעך אני, mashbiacha ani, I make you take an
oath. And he says אמן, amen, yes, and he takes the oath.
ועדים מעידים אותו שגנבו, ve'eidim mei'idim oto sheganavo, and the witnesses say
it's you that kept it to yourself. That's where that תנא קמא,
tanna kamma, ונמצא שהוא גנבו, venimtza shehu ganavo, משלם תשלומי כפל, meshallem
tashlumei kefel, that's when you pay double. And here, if you admit,
it actually lowers your liability. הודה מעצמו, hodeh mei'atzmo, because כפל kefel,
remember is a קנס. kenas. So if you admit, you're not going
to pay the כפל. kefel So if you admit, then you go
back to this קרבן korban of אשם גזילות asham gezelot of using
an oath to steal something, which is משלם קרן וחומש, meshallem keren
vechomesh, the base and the fifth, that's the atonement, ואשם ve'asham and
the sacrifice. Okay, so anyway, that's about bringing the קרבן korban which
is not our interest, but our interest is that you pay כפל
kefel. when you claim it was stolen and you take an oath,
and not when you claim that it was lost and take an
oath. Now, קתני מיהא, katani miha, we teach nevertheless, בטוען טענת גנב,
beto'en ta'anat ganav, when you make a claim that it was burgled,
דמשלם תשלומי כפל. demeshallem tashlumei kefel. אבל בטוען טענת אבדה, aval beto'en
ta'anat aveidah, if you say it was just lost, לא משלם תשלומי
כפל, lo meshallem tashlumei kefel, you don't pay double.
ואפילו טוען טענת גנב, ve'afilu to'en ta'anat ganav, this גמרא gemara is
very wordy, even when you do a טענת גנב, ta'anat ganav, בשבועה
דמשלם תשלומי כפל, bishvuah demeshallem tashlumei kefel, only when you take an
oath. אבל שלא בשבועה, aval shelo bishvuah, if you just claimed it
and you were lying without having taken an oath, אינו משלם תשלומי
כפל, eino meshallem tashlumei kefel, you don't. You need those two criteria.
מני הני מילי, mani hanei milei, where does this come from in
the פסוקים? psukim דתנו רבנן, detanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: אם ימצא
הגנב, im yimatze haganav, right? אם ימצא הגנב im yimatze haganav. ישלם
שנים. shnayim, Okay, אם לא ימצא הגנב ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלוקים.
im lo yimatze haganav venikrav ba'al habayit el ha'elokim. So the first
half is אם ימצא הגנב. im yimatze haganav, בטוען טענת גנב הכתוב
מדבר. beto'en ta'anat ganav hakatuv medabber. So this whole thing, the simple
sense is this is talking about you really found the גנב, ganav,
and this is talking about somehow you claimed what happened to it
and you were brought into court. So the first דרשה derashah is
going to say both of these scenarios are טוען טענת גנב, to'en
ta'anat ganav, which is a strange read. Then we're going to have
another version that says no, this is about finding the actual גנב,
ganav and this is about טוען טענת גנב. to'en ta'anat ganav. Okay,
but the first read is that both of them are טוען טענת
גנב. to'en ta'anat ganav. בטוען טענת גנב הכתוב מדבר. beto'en ta'anat ganav
hakatuv medabber. אתה אומר בטוען טענת גנב הכתוב מדבר. atah omer beto'en
ta'anat ganav hakatuv medabber. You're saying the first half is talking about
a guy that claimed it was stolen. או אינו אלא בגנב עצמו,
o eino ella beganav atzmo, maybe it's only about the גנב ganav
himself pays כפל, kefel. that is the simple sense of the first
half? No, כשהוא אומר אם לא ימצא הגנב, keshehu omer im lo
yimatze haganav, בטוען טענת גנב הכתוב מדבר. beto'en ta'anat ganav hakatuv medabber.
Since the second part is, right, I mean, I left out the
key part here that we're דורשין dorshin right now, this is, here,
here's אם ימצא הגנב,
im yimatze
haganav, then it's ישלם שנים. אם לא ימצא הגנב, im lo yimatze
haganav,
then ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלוקים. venikrav ba'al habayit el ha'elokim. Okay,
so it's saying since this part here is clearly the גנב ganav,
wasn't found and you took an oath and you were
lying, and this is that there was no גנב, ganav, it's just
your claim, so presumably the first half is also there was no
real גנב, ganav it was just your claim, which is of course
bizarre. The whole difference between the first half and the second
half, anyway, but that's the claim. Since the bottom half is about
טוען טענת גנב, to'en ta'anat ganav, the first half is about טוען
טענת גנב. to'en ta'anat ganav. That's first version. תניא אידך, tanya idach,
the second ברייתא braita makes more sense. אם ימצא הגנב, haganav if
the גנב ganav is found, בגנב עצמו הכתוב מדבר. beganav atzmo hakatuv
medabber. The first half is that there was a real גנב ganav
and the real גנב ganav pays double. אתה אומר בגנב עצמו או
אינו אלא בטוען טענת גנב, atah omer beganav atzmo o eino ella
beto'en ta'anat ganav, maybe the first half is about the guy claimed
he was the
גנב ganav and he was lying? No, that's the second half of
the פסוק. pasuk, כשהוא אומר אם לא ימצא הגנב, keshehu omer im
lo yimatze haganav, if the גנב ganav isn't found, behold, that's the
second half of the פסוק, pasuk, and then there was a claim
what had happened etc., that's הרי טוען טענת גנב. harei to'en ta'anat
ganav. That's the guy who claimed that it was stolen. אם כן
מה אני מקיים אם ימצא הגנב, im ken mah ani mekayyem im
yimatze haganav, what's the first half of the פסוק pasuk that the
גנב ganav. was found? בגנב עצמו הכתוב מדבר. beganav atzmo hakatuv medabber.
The real גנב. ganav Okay, so that's obviously the simple sense. It
was stolen, it was burgled, the גנב ganav pays double. It wasn't
actually, or the burglar isn't found and there's a claim, and that's
the whole thing about you making a claim about what happened. Okay,
דכולי עלמא מיהא, dekhullei alma miha, everybody agrees nonetheless, אם לא ימצא
הגנב, im lo yimatze haganav the second half of the פסוק, pasuk
the גנב ganav wasn't found, בטוען טענת גנב כתיב, beto'en ta'anat ganav
ketiv, it's talking that you are making a claim that it was
stolen. מאי משמע, mai mashma, where do you get that from the
second half of the פסוק, pasuk, that that's what's going on, right?
Because the second half of the פסוק pasuk, is extremely vague. It
says if the גנב ganav isn't found, you come to the court
and that you didn't abuse the object. object, and the person who
is the wrongdoer pays double. Like what? What did you exactly say
in the court? Who’s paying double? Like the whole half of the
second פסוק pasuk is not clear. So מאי משמע, mai mashma, where
do you get that from? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אם לא ימצא
הגנב כמו שאמר אלא שהוא עצמו גנבו. im lo yimatze haganav kemo
she'amar, ela she'hu atzmo genavo. So אם לא ימצא הגנב im lo
yimatze haganav. doesn’t just mean that the actual burglar wasn’t found. The
burglar wasn’t found, how do we know there was a burglar if
the burglar isn’t found? Because you claim there was a burglar. So,
and he wasn’t found, but rather what happened, it turns out you’re
the burglar. So, of course, that still doesn’t answer how we know
that’s what it’s talking about. You just read all of that into
the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, but that’s how we’re reading it into the
פסוקים. psukim It doesn’t prove it’s what the פסוקים psukim. are talking
about, but it says how we’re reading it into the פסוקים. psukim
אם לא ימצא im lo yimatze if the גנב ganav isn’t found
because you claim there was a גנב ganav but nobody can find
the גנב ganav. because guess what? There wasn’t really a גנב. ganav.
Okay, אלא שהוא עצמו גנבו, ela she'hu atzmo genavo, the guy himself
was the גנב. ganav In that case ישלם שנים. All right, so
again, that’s how we read it into the פסוק, pasuk not how—that
doesn’t prove that’s what the פסוקים psukim? are talking about.
ומנלן דבשבועה? Uminlan d'bishvua? Now how do we know that there’s a
שבועה shvua going on here? It just says you come to the
court, it never says that you took an oath. דתניא Detanya we
learn a ברייתא. braisa. ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים Venikrav ba'al habayis
el ha'elohim then you’re brought in front of the judges. לשבועה, L'shvua,
you have to take an oath about what happened. אתה אומר לשבועה
אינו אלא לדין? At omer l'shvua, einu ela l'din? Maybe it just
means that there’s a court case? No. נאמר שליחות יד למטה ונאמר
שליחות יד למעלה. Ne'emar shlichus yad lemata ven'emar shlichus yad lemala. Later
it’s going to talk about that it says you take an oath,
a שומר shomer takes an oath. It says שבועת ה' תהיה בין
שניהם אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. shvuat Hashem tihye bein shneihem
im lo shalach yado bimleches re'eihu. Okay, so later by שומרים shomrim
it’s going to say you have to take an oath that you
did not misuse the object. So מה להלן לשבועה, ma lahan l'shvua,
the same way there it’s explicit that you did not misuse the
object is with an oath, אף כאן לשבועה. af kan l'shvua. Here
too, right? Because remember it says ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים אם
לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו venikrav ba'al habayis el ha'elohim im lo
shalach yado bimleches re'eihu that did you not misuse it. So here
the גמרא Gemara is saying, and this actually, you know, makes a
lot of sense, that later we see that a שומר shomer. has
to take an oath that he did not misuse it, and he
uses the same phrase אם לא שלח ידו. So to say that
this line means you make an oath, that’s a reasonable interpretation. Okay,
but again it’s very
cryptic. The גנב ganav isn’t clear—isn’t found, there’s some שבועה shvua taken,
you pay double. Like, somebody is paying double, why? So the גמרא
Gemara reads into it: you’re paying double because you lied, you said
it was stolen and you lied. Okay, so בשלמא למאן דאמר חד
בגנב וחד בטוען טענת גנב, bishlama l'man d'amar chad b'ganav v'chad b'toen
taanat ganav, if you say the first case in the Torah is
גנב ganav, and the second is a claim of a גנב, ganav
so then we
understand, היינו דתרי קראי. hainu d'trei krai. That's why you have two
sets of פסוקים. A גנב ganav pays כפל kefel, and a guy
who claims there was a גנב ganav, pays
כפל. kefel? אלא למאן דאמר תרוייהו בטוען טענת גנב, Ela l'man d'amar
travaihu b'toen taanat ganav, but if both of the פסוקים are talking
about a claim of a גנב, ganav תרי קראי למה לי? trei
krai lama li? Why do I need two פסוקים? Two scenarios? I
mean, they’re the same scenario. אמינא לך חד למעוטי טענת אבדה וחד
למעוטי טענת אבדה. Amina lach chad l'imutei taanat avada v'chad l'imutei taanat
avada. So yes, one is to tell you the basic הלכה halacha
of טוען טענת גנב, toen taanat ganav, and then it repeats the
הלכה halacha of טוען טענת גנב toen taanat ganav to tell you
that this הלכה halacha would not apply if you claimed it was
lost. The הלכה halacha only applies if you—if you swear that it
was stolen or burgled, but if you swear that it was lost,
you’re not going to pay double. So גמרא Gemara says, ולמאן דאמר
חד בגנב וחד בטוען טענת גנב, u'l'man d'amar chad b'ganav v'chad b'toen
taanat ganav, according to the one that one is about a גנב
ganav, and one is about a claim of a גנב, ganav. דלא
מיותר, d'lo miyater, למעוטי טענת אבדה מנלן? l'imutei taanat avada minlan? He
doesn’t have an extra פרשה, parsha, so how does he know that
the הלכה halacha does not apply when you make an oath that
it was lost? So מגנב הגנב. m'ganav haganav. It says אם לא
ימצא הגנב. haganav? So הגנב haganav, means a real גנב. ganav, All
of this would apply only when it’s a real claim about a
גנב, ganav, not a claim about it being lost. ולמאן דאמר תרוייהו
בטוען טענת גנב, u'l'man d'amar travaihu b'toen taanat ganav, and the one
that says both of them is about a claim of a גנב,
ganav? למעוטי טוען טענת אבדה—it’s l'imutei toen taanat avada so wordy here—למעוטי
טוען טענת אבדה l'imutei toen taanat avada that he already knows that
to exclude the claim of being lost from the double פרשה—from parsha
the repeated פרשה, parsha, גנב הגנב ganav haganav מאי דריש ביה? mai
darish bei? What does he do with the extra hei: הגנב? haganav
אמר לך, amar lach, he’ll tell you, מיבעי ליה לכדרבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. mibaye lei l'chider'ebbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan. Like what we taught. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan because we’re quoting
Rabbi יוחנן, Yochanan, הטוען טענת גנב בפקדון משלם תשלומי כפל. ha'toen taanat
ganav b'pikadon meshalem tashlumei kefel. Where you claim that it was stolen
and it wasn’t, you’re lying, you pay double. Now let’s say it
was a sheep or an ox that you were watching and you
say it was stolen and you take an oath. And now after
the בעל הבית goes away, you slaughter it or you sell it.
Are you going to pay four or five? How much are you
fully like a גנב? ganav Right, all we know so far is
that if you take a false oath that it was stolen you
pay כפל. kefel. But a real גנב ganav. who would then after
the burglary would slaughter or sell it would pay four or five,
right? How do—would that apply to you too? So we’re going to
say yes. So he says... טבח
ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. tovach umachar meshalem tashlumei arba'ah vachamisha. So
גנב הגנב ganav haganav rather than actually coming to limit is coming
to emphasize: You, you are a full גנב. ganav You claimed it
was stolen, you are הגנב, you are just like the גנב ganav,
himself, and you're going to pay four five times. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, למאן דאמר חד בגנב וחד בטוען טענת גנב דהאי
גנב
הגנב אתא למיעוט טענת אבד. le-man de-amar chad be-ganav ve-chad be-to'en ta'anat
ganav de-hai ganav haganav ata le-mi'ut ta'anat avad. And according to the
one that says this is about a גנב, ganav, this is טוען
טענת גנב to'en ta'anat ganav and the הגנב says it does not
play pay it does it's only by a claim of גניבה, not
by a claim of אבידה. So למיעוט אבד, le-mi'ut avad, רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר מנא ליה? Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar mna
lei?
Where does he know this הלכה halacha that if you slaughter it
or sell it, you would pay four or five? אמר לך היקשא
הוא ואין משיבין על ההיקשא. Amar lach hekesha hu ve-ein meshivin al
ha-hekesha. Oh, you learn it out from the juxtaposition. Here's a גנב,
ganav. here's a טוען טענת גנב. to'en ta'anat ganav. So, and so
the same way in this case you pay four or five in
a case of a sheep or an ox, in this case you
would pay four or five. Okay, so now by the way though,
this is really fascinating. You just said with your words, you just
made a claim that this is what happened, and we give you
the full status of a גנב. ganav, You not only pay כפל,
kefel but if you slaughter it or sell it, you're going to
pay four or five. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. בשלמא
למאן דאמר חד בגנב וחד בטוען טענת גנב שפיר. Bishlama le-man de-amar
chad be-ganav ve-chad be-to'en ta'anat ganav shapir. If one's about a גנב,
ganav, one's about a claim of a גנב, ganav, good, it makes
sense. אלא למאן דאמר תרוייהו בטוען טענת גנב גנב עצמו מנא ליה?
Ela le-man de-amar travaihu be-to'en ta'anat ganav ganav atzmo mna lei? Finally
that question. If the whole thing is here about claim of a
גנב, ganav how do you know a real גנב ganav pays double?
Now, you might want to make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but
okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like that.
וכי תימא ליתי בקל וחומר מטוען טענת גנב? Ve-chi teima leitei be-kal
vachomer mi-to'en ta'anat ganav? No. דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון. Dayo
la-ba min ha-din li-hyot ke-nidon.
It should be limited by that case itself. מה להלן בשבועה, Mah
le-hallan bi-shvu'ah, the same way by making a claim that it was
נגנב you pay double only when you do it through a שבועה,
shvu'ah, אף כאן בשבועה. af kan bi-shvu'ah. Maybe a גנב ganav himself
will only pay double if he makes some oath that he didn't
steal it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, נפקא ליה מדתנא דבי
חזקיה. Nafka lei mi-de-tana d-vei Chizkiyah. No, which we learn out that
a real גנב ganav pays double from what דבי חזקיה d-vei Chizkiyah
teaches. דתנא דבי חזקיה, De-tana d-vei Chizkiyah, because דבי חזקיה d-vei Chizkiyah
teaches, יאמר שור וגניבה והכל בכלל. Yomar shor u-gneivah ve-hakol bi-khlal.
Why doesn't it just say, now here actually there's another פסוק, pasuk
okay, that says you pay double. The פסוק pasuk, is אם המצא
תמצא בידו הגנבה. Im hematzei timatzei be-yado ha-gneivah. אם המצא תמצא בידו
הגנבה, Im hematzei timatzei be-yado ha-gneivah, משור
עד—what's the פסוק? pasuk. משור עד
חמור עד שה חיים,
Mi-shor ad
chamor ad seh chayim, משור עד חמור עד שה
חיים שנים ישלם.
mi-shor ad chamor
ad seh chayim shnayim yeshalem.
So if you slaughter it, right, you pay—or you sell it, you
could pay four or five. Yes, that's the other הלכה. halacha. But
let's say המצא תמצא בידו
הגנבה. himatzei timatzei be-yado ha-gneivah. So it's בידו, be-yado, what did you
not do? You didn't sell it. And it is חיים. chayim. So
what also did you not do? You didn't slaughter it. So if
you didn't sell it and you didn't slaughter it, then you're going
to pay שנים, okay? So that is a classic פסוק of a
גנב ganav paying double. So you don't need a גנב ganav paying
double down here in the middle of this complicated case of a
שומר. Just tell me you pay there, it's explicit. If you slaughtered
or sold it, you pay four or five. If you didn't slaughter
or sell it, you're going to pay double. Okay, and that's what
you know a גנב ganav pays double. So let's look at that.
Okay, so מדתנא דבי חזקיה. mi-de-tana d-vei Chizkiyah. דתנא דבי חזקיה. De-tana
d-vei Chizkiyah. יאמר שור וגניבה והכל בכלל. Yomar shor u-gneivah ve-hakol bi-khlal.
We're back to now why do you need all these specifics? משור
עד חמור עד שה חיים. Mi-shor ad chamor ad seh chayim. Okay.
אילו כן, Ilu ken, if it had just said שור הגנבה משור,
shor ha-gneivah mi-shor, הייתי אומר מה פרט מפורש קרב לגבי מזבח אף
כל קרב לגבי מזבח. hayiti omer mah prat meforash karev legabei mizbe'ach
af kol karev legabei mizbe'ach. Only things that are brought as sacrifices.
אף כל קרב לגבי מזבח. af kol karev legabei mizbe'ach. So maybe
limit double paying to that. מה יש לך להביא שה? Mah yesh
lecha le-havi seh? So what would have been included?
I would say sacrifices, and that includes a שה, seh a sheep.
כשהוא אומר שה, Ke-she-hu omer seh, but then it explicitly says sheep.
So that's coming to broaden it. הרי שה אמור מה אני מקיים
גניבה Harei seh amur mah ani mekayem gneivah לרבות כל דבר. le-rabot
kol davar.
So that means everything. But one minute. יאמר שור ושה וגניבה והכל
בכלל. Yomar shor ve-seh u-gneivah ve-hakol bi-khlal. Why didn't it just say
מגניבה עד שור עד שה? mi-gneivah ad shor ad seh? Why did
it have to add חמור? chamor. אילו כן הייתי אומר מה פרט
מפורש דבר הקדוש בבכורה אף כל דבר הקדוש בבכורה. Ilu ken hayiti
omer mah prat meforash davar ha-kadosh bi-vkhorah af kol davar ha-kadosh bi-vkhorah.
I would have said, the same way the specific detail is something
sanctified by being the firstborn, everything is something sanctified by the firstborn,
and I would have limited it to that. מה יש לך להביא?
Mah yesh lecha le-havi? And then what would I have broadened שור
and שה to be, to include other things that are sanctified with
בכורה, be-khorah, which includes what? חמור, a donkey. But then it went
and had to say חמור. כשהוא אומר חמור הרי חמור אמור מה
אני מקיים גניבה לרבות כל דבר. Ke-she-hu omer chamor harei chamor amur
mah ani mekayem gneivah le-rabot kol davar. Okay.
So it says משור עד חמור עד שה. mi-shor ad chamor ad
seh. So if it was just meant to limit it... To מזבח
mizbeach or to קדש בבכורה kadosh bivchorah or whatever, it wouldn't have
said all three of those. It would have been I could have
anyway gotten that. So by saying all of those, it's coming to
broaden it even more. All right? But one minute. יאמר שור וחמור
ושה וגנבה וכל בכל. yomar shor vechamor veseh ugneivah vechol bakol. אילו
כך, ilu kach, with that, I would have said מה פרט מפורש
בעלי חיים, mah prat meforash ba'alei chayim, maybe it's just coming to
limit to all animals. אף כל בעלי חיים. af kol ba'alei chayim.
So even all, מה יש לך להביא שאר בעלי חיים, mah yesh
lecha lehavi shear ba'alei chayim, you would have included all animals. כשהוא
אומר חיים, keshehu omer chayim, so maybe the כלל פרט וכלל klal
prat u'klal is just only by animals, not by non-animals. But then
it would... but the word חיים chayim already means here, not the
way we explained it, which was פשט pshat that you hadn't slaughtered
it, but means any animal. So if all it wanted to do
was broaden it to animals, just say חיים. chayim. Why does it
say שור חמור ושה shor chamor veseh whatever? That we're not limiting
ourselves just to animals. הרי חיים אמור. harei chayim amur. הא מני
מקיים גנבה לרבות כל דבר, ha mani mekayem gneivah l'ravos kol davar,
to include everything. So what this is the source, meaning remember, the
question was if all of this is טוען טענת גנב, to'ein ta'anas
ganav, how do you know כפל? kefel And the answer is you've
got an explicit פסוק that a גנב pays כפל. kefel But now
we're going to look at this פסוק, because here we were looking
how do you know כפל includes all things and we did our
own little כלל פרט וכלל. klal prat u'klal. Now we're going up
here and saying how do you know כפל includes all things? Maybe
it's only animals. So again, if it were more limited, you wouldn't
have needed all of these cases. Because it says all of these
things, that's going to tell us that you're going to pay כפל
on the whole universe of things.
Why didn't they start with that?
I know, that's the most, that's the clearest פסוק. Okay, we will
continue tomorrow.